Welcome to AP US History Unit 6. This
unit we will cover basically everything
about the Guilded Age and it is worth 10
to 17% on your AP exam. This video is
probably one of the most highly
requested ones I've ever had on this
channel. So for anyone that's new here,
this video will be a clip together video
of all my A push unit 6 topic review
videos without the AP style questions at
the end of each video. If you'd like to
attempt AP style questions that
correspond to each topic of unit 6, you
can find my A push unit 6 playlist in
the description of this video. Please do
consider following my Instagram. It's
honestly all I ask in return for making
these videos. But anyway, let's get into
unit 6. Unit 6 is here and we transition
into a new time period of American
history. We covered antibbellum, the
Civil War, and reconstruction, which are
all viable eras of American history.
Now, we transition into a new era called
the Gilded Age. This era will be
explored throughout this unit, but the
biggest thing to notice is that the US
will slowly start becoming controlled by
the rich throughout this era, not the
government. Of course, there will be
three big causes of this. Westward
expansion, the industrial revolution,
and capitalism. Right now, we will
simply talk about the westward expansion
part of it. So, let's recap. The Civil
War and reconstruction has ended. Yes,
this has left devastation all around the
country, but it also has left one other
big thing, an unbelievable level of
manufacturing. The big things here were
factories, steel, and railroads.
Railroads were especially exciting
because they could move a lot of goods
very fast, and the government made them
cheap to build. And that is why the
transcontinental railroad was ordered to
be built from the east to the west. Why
go to the west, you ask? It's simple.
Gold. So much gold was found in places
like modern-day Colorado, California,
Nevada, and many other places that many
settlers saw as a chance to get rich. It
also helped that at this time it was
really easy to move west because the
government still had the Homestead Act
in place along with various subsidies to
incentivize expansion. Farmers got a
bunch of new farming innovations like
barbed wire and steamed powered
equipment. And most importantly, the
West offered new land to farm and mine
on. With thousands of people moving
west, many communities formed. I
personally cannot be asked to go over
them, but here are some if you really
care to read about them. Now, here's
where things get muddy. Though there
isn't a technical start of the Guilded
Age, this is how the Gilded Age
essentially starts. There's only one way
a farmer or miner in the West is going
to transport their goods back to the
east. Railroads. The owners of these
railroads knew this and raised the
prices on everyone, especially small
businesses. This led to farmers creating
groups and alliances such as the
Graange, the Farmers Alliance, and the
Colored Farmers Alliance. But remember
what I said earlier, the rich are in
control in this time period. And so it's
no surprise that all of these for the
most part failed. In this time period,
farmers relied on bank loans and the
influx of farming goods caused prices to
drop, making it so farmers suffered
quite a bit from debt. Remember, this
video is only one of three separate
causes of the guilded age. There are
still others you have to consider. So we
already know this. Settlers are moving
west because of gold opportunity farming
blah blah blah. Now we are going to talk
about the effects of this. So we already
talked about the transcontinental
railroad. What we didn't talk about was
that the people building this railroad
were mostly Chinese and Irish
immigrants. And understand that this was
no easy job. A very dangerous explosive
called nitroglycerin was constantly used
to blow out tunnels and it would make it
very dangerous to work on these
railroads. Another thing to note is this
animal right here. In 1860, there were
an estimated 30 million bison in the
United States. By 1884, there were less
than a thousand. So, how the heck did
this happen? Well, railroads split the
herds. Companies hired hunters to kill
them for hides. And the US military
encouraged killing them to force native
tribes off the plains. But that isn't
even talking about the worst part. Let's
look at our standard US map. West. Well,
what is west? Gold, obviously, right?
No, I mean the people actually
originally inhabiting the land. Yeah,
Native Americans still exist and they
are still trying to live freely in the
west. But by this point, Americans had
so many incentives to move west that
they didn't just ignore native peoples,
they actively despised them simply for
living on the land. Treaties that once
promised native sovereignty were
completely violated. America would
switch to a reservation policy and force
native tribes to live on specific
reservation lands. And this did not sue
many native cultures. So did the natives
fight back? Of course they did. It
started with Sand Creek, which was the
first major show of federal betrayal.
The Red River War ended native
resistance in Texas and Oklahoma. The
Nez Perse War ended organized resistance
in the Northwest. The Apache Wars
dragged on for decades, but ended when
the Donimo surrendered in 1886. Now,
there were native victories, too, like
the Sue Wars and the Battle of Little
Bigghorn, but those winds were
temporary. Everything all came crashing
down with the DAW act in 1887. This
divided native land into private plots,
giving the quote surplus to white
settlers. This led to the loss of over
90 million acres of native land. And
around the same time, a spiritual
movement called the ghost dance spread
among tribes. It symbolized hope for a
world without white domination. And of
course, the US white dominated military
saw it as a threat. And it all
culminated in the Wounded Knee Massacre.
This would kill 300 natives and end the
so-called Indian Wars across America.
The Indians being the obvious losers. If
you can't tell, America are not the good
guys here. They took land they promised
not to take and killed thousands in the
process. In fact, if you live in any of
these states, you are living on
technical stolen land as we speak. It's
unfortunately one of the darkest parts
of American history. It's been a while
since we've talked about them. So, let's
go check on our good old friends, the
South. We've known up to this point that
the South has an economy that is
essentially entirely based on
agriculture. And up until the Civil War,
that agriculture was essentially all
done by slaves. So now, when the war and
reconstruction are over, a journalist
named Henry Grady sees this and starts
petitioning the South to modernize and
adopt the industrial practices of the
North and turn themselves into a quote
new South. Now, this does gain
attention. The North funds the South to
build mills, mines, and factories, and
big industrial cities form such as
Charlotte and Atlanta. But even with all
this industry getting introduced, this
quote new south will continue to rely on
farming and sharecropping for its
primary economic base. So on the
surface, the new south is marked by a
switch to industry when in reality
agriculture still remains the primary
economic driver. However, the other part
to this is the role of African-Ameans.
And this is where you see the big
contradiction of the new south. Because
while the south talked a big game about
modernization and progress, socially and
politically, it was still stuck in the
past. White [music] supremacy didn't
disappear at all. And the clearest
example of this is the Supreme Court
case Py v. Ferguson, which ruled that
racial segregation laws, known as Jim
Crow laws, were constitutional as long
as facilities were quote separate but
equal. In practice, this whole separate
but equal thing never actually worked
out. African-Americans constantly
received worse facilities, fewer
resources, and almost zero legal
protection. Convict leasing, lynchings,
pole taxes, and unfair literacy tests
were all still very common across the
South. Now, there were people who
advocated for African-American rights,
such as Booker T. Washington, who
emphasized economic self-help and
education, and journalists like Ida B.
Wells directly challenged lynchings and
racial violence. But with these Jim Crow
laws now being considered
constitutional, it would be hard for any
real civil rights to appear until quite
a bit later. So, the guilded age. When I
see this era of American history, what I
think of is governmental corruption, big
business, and disgustingly rich people
having power over the government. All
that stuff we will get to in our next
topic. But for this topic, what we need
to talk about is the sheer amount of
industrialization that happened during
the guilded age. You might remember the
market revolution. In the early 1800s,
you had people making machines. During
the guilded age, you now have machines
making machines. In the past, industry
relied on iron. Now, with the Bessemer
process, steel is what takes over. In
the market revolution, factories ran on
steam. Now, everything runs on
electricity and it transforms
production. And the other part of this
is now with all this new railroad
expansion, the US has access to so much
land and that land is a literal gold
mine of resources such as coal, iron,
oil, timber, copper, etc. But anyway,
you see what's happening here. We have
so many resources and a lot of new
innovations. This will make large-scale
businesses. These businesses will become
extremely popular. The people owning
these businesses will get really rich.
The US will stand down and adopt a lair
capitalist economic policy. And there
you go. That's the Gilded Age coming to
life. In a previous video, I said the
three causes of the Gilded Age were
westward expansion, the industrial
revolution, and capitalism. We already
covered the West, so now it's time to
talk about the other two, starting with
the industrial revolution. And when I
say the industrial revolution, I mean
the second industrial revolution. And
even though that's considered a more
European term, with how much
industrialization happened during the
Gilded Age, it is fair to call what
happened a second industrial revolution.
During the guilded age, all the new
technology led to businesses wanting to
capitalize on the production or rather
the mass production of the goods. There
was a really big workforce because of a
bunch of new immigration and the
government policies heavily favored
businesses. And that is where we get to
throw in a key term, industrial
capitalism. This is where private
individuals own the means of production
like factories and machinery to generate
profit through wage-based labor by
mass-producing goods. Since this would
be popularized, it would mean the
capitalist LZ afair economic system
would become mostly standard in the
United States, meaning that it is the
third cause of the guilded age. Now we
turn to the consequences of this
industrial expansion which facilitated
the rise of three dominant corporate
figures of the guilded age. John D.
Rockefeller, Andrew Carnegie, and JP
Morgan. Rockefeller was probably the
richest man in American history. He
coined horizontal integration where he'd
buy out all of his rivals and he led the
oil industry. Carnegie on the other hand
coined vertical integration where he
controlled each and every means of
production and led the steel industry
and Morgan's the bank guy meaning he
controlled like finance or something.
Stuff like trusts were set up along with
many companies holding stock in other
companies known as holding companies
which resulted in entire industries like
oil and steel to be completely
monopolized. And these businesses would
even seek out markets outside of America
in all of these places on the screen.
And this would be the economic prelude
to American imperialism. As for the
government, initially what we see are
weak Supreme Court decisions and the
poorly enforced Sherman Antirust Act,
which meant the government really
couldn't do anything to combat this
guilded age. And yes, it is definitely
fair to say that these corporate giants
use their deep pockets to influence
American politics. So, you might ask,
what is the result of all of this? Well,
I'll tell you. This would cause a
disproportionate share of American
wealth to be accumulated amongst a very
few top elite. Small businesses now
don't stand a chance. Monopolies would
cause prices on goods to go up and most
of all workers would be paid horribly in
these factories and had almost no power
to bargain otherwise. Very quickly, this
will cause these quote captives of
industry to be referred to as robber
barons because honestly that is kind of
what they are. This would lead to a
movement later known as progressivism,
but I get ahead of myself. So, it's time
to talk about the societal impact of the
guilded age. And to put it into
perspective, I will say three things
that will be hard to believe. During the
guilded age, prices on goods mostly went
down. Workers real wages actually
increased and most people's standard of
living actually improved. So that sounds
great, right? Wrong. Yes, mass
production lowered prices, and yes,
wages rose on paper, but that didn't
mean workers lived well. Most industrial
workers earned barely enough to survive,
lived in overcrowded tenement housing,
and worked brutal hours in unsafe
factories. And cheaper goods don't
matter much when your life is already
miserable. Yeah. So, why don't we play a
fun game? Now, I imagine most of my
audience consists of the typical teenage
target worker. So, let's compare what
labor is like for a modern-day Target
position compared to a guilded age
factory position. Well, first, at
Target, you are only allowed to work 8
hours a day. I mean, it's standard,
obviously. Now, moving over to the
guilded age. Yikes. That's rough, buddy.
But, okay. Okay. At least Target has the
ironclad rule of no child labor for
anyone under the age of 16. Oh, but
what's with all these photos during the
guilded age of kids working? It's almost
as if in the past child labor was
extremely common. But don't worry, at
least at Target, you're not going to get
horribly injured. And if you do, you'll
at least have workers comp to pay for
it. Well, here's the guilded age.
That's right. There are no safety
regulations, frequent injuries, child
labor, no workers comp, long hours, no
breaks, no helmets, no guards, no
warnings.
>> 5 minutes later. So, you get the idea.
Because of these horrid circumstances,
some workers united together into unions
that would protest this. Here are a few
examples. The Knights of Labor was a
union who accepted people of all skills,
genders, and races. They argued for
8-hour work days, no child labor, and
equal pay. It's too bad that they were
horribly unorganized and they were also
unfortunately blamed for this next
thing, the Hey Market affair. The story
goes, workers were protesting against
police violence against workers. One
thing led to another. Someone threw a
bomb and there you go, 11 people died.
And finally, the Pullman company's
workers went on strike. The big deal
with this one is that it showed complete
obvious proof that the government would
side with businesses over the common
citizen. So yeah, early on workers are
still going to be under horrible
conditions. But don't worry, there is a
reason the next era is called the
progressive era. There is a big
workforce in all of these factories. So
you might wonder who exactly comprises
this workforce. Simply put, it's mostly
immigrants. Like obviously there are a
lot of prim and proper Americans in the
batch, but it was mostly immigrants. To
basically oversimplify this, not just
America, but the entire world is getting
privy to the knowledge of all the jobs
available in the United States. And a
lot of people wanted to come over and
start a new life. And also it helped
that life in these immigrants homelands
were not really that great, especially
if they were uniquely religious. The two
big waves of immigration you'll see are
people coming in from Europe to the east
coast and those coming in from Asia on
the west coast. This will lead to the
formation of two big hubs of immigrant
processing. Ellis Island right outside
of New York City and Angel Island right
outside of San Francisco. So let me
quickly explain something. If you're an
Uncle Sam American in this time period
with your own twisted racial beliefs on
the Ellis Island side, of course you're
going to want the lovely, hardworking,
mostly white Europeans in America
because they will create a better
society. But those Asians on the Angel
Island side, um, uh, so yeah, what I
mean is that in this time period, Ellis
Island was known as very welcoming. It
even had health checks and was seen as a
mostly great place. Angel Island, on the
other hand, was home to countless
interrogations, detentions, and long,
long stays, all instigated by deeply
rooted anti-Asian racism. And though
unrelated, here's a picture of me many,
many years ago on Angel Island. There's
no real historical significance here. I
honestly just wanted to show off that
I've been there. Anyway, the outcome of
all of this immigration is the formation
of lots of ethnic inclaves. This era is
the pure reason why there are things
like Chinatowns, Little Italies, Jewish
neighborhoods, and much more ethnic
areas around the US. We also see a lot
of internal migration in this time
period as well. For example, you have
lots of people from the rural
countryside moving into urban cities.
And finally, a bunch of
African-Americans are moving out of the
south cuz honestly, screw that goddamn
place. This would set the stage for
something later known as the Great
Migration. I think it's fair to say that
all the immigration coming into the
United States during this guilded age
was not that wellreceived by American
society. America has mostly always stood
on the principle of the acceptance of
any sort of immigration. At least that's
what they say on the surface. Behind the
scenes, there was a lot of debates and
quite a bit of governmental action as
well. So, let's give a few examples.
First of all, do you remember all those
Chinese immigrants that risk their lives
to do dangerous work building the
transcontinental railroad? Well, here's
a fun story. There was so much
anti-Asian racism that by 1882, America
passed the Chinese Exclusion Act that
put a 10-year ban on any new Chinese
labor immigration. But you also have
good things, too. Like, for example, in
the Supreme Court case US versus Wong
Kim Arc, it established and solidified
birthright citizenship, meaning anyone
born in the US is a US citizen. A good
book to reference here might be Rose
Cohan's Out of the Shadow. This book
follows the tale of Rose who immigrated
into the US as a Jewish immigrant and
shows her struggles to maintain her
culture as she worked through countless
sweat shops. Another thing to note here
is the work of women or more
specifically one woman named Jane Adams.
She's known for doing quite a lot of
stuff. But for this time period, what
you should know is that she co-founded
the famous whole house where she would
aid the poor along with immigrants. Also
during this time, you have people all
over the place wanting to justify their
class, race or just status in society.
And this is where an ideology takes hold
known as social Darwinism. Essentially,
what this means is applying the quote
survival of the fittest ideal to
society. Or for a better definition,
social Darwinism argues that the strong
naturally dominate the weak and that
social inequality, racism, and
imperialism are justified as natural
outcomes of competition. Now, of course,
I'm not even going to get into how this
is completely wrong and how it
completely misapplies Charles Darwin's
original thinking. Rather, I just want
you to know that this very controversial
ideology was used in this time period to
justify the success of those on top of
the social ladder. And like throughout
this entire unit, all I've done is talk
about how the rich are living gray and
the poor are not. And yes, that is true.
But there are quite a few people outside
of the top of the top and the bottom of
the bottom that actually benefited from
the guilded age. This group of people
would be the new emerging middle class.
Let me tell you why this middle class
actually formed. Going back to this
triangle, you have the ultra rich up at
the top and the povertystricken factory
workers at the bottom. But those weren't
the only two jobs that were needed in
this era. Big businesses like factories
also require a lot of white collar work,
meaning things like managers,
accountants, clerks, typists,
secretaries, salespeople, etc. were
needed. And these jobs paid better than
factory work and were way safer. Most of
the clerical work that was available at
a lower level will actually mostly be
taken by the women in society. The other
thing this ties into is education. Lots
of these jobs require a formal education
to understand them, which is where the
moral act of 1862 comes in. This act
gave federal land to states. And in
exchange, the states would use the land
to build institutions like colleges to
teach all the skills needed for these
white collar jobs. This is where we
start seeing teacher training or
business education and a new importance
to professional credentials. And also,
since there's now actually a decent
amount of people in the middle class
with disposable income and leisure time,
the first modern consumer culture
develops, things like amusement parks
such as Coney Island or maybe department
stores or a plethora of other things.
Also, let's talk about the rich really
quickly. Social Darwinism argued that
inequality between the rich and the poor
is natural, which mainly just gave poor
people another reason to resent the
wealthy. So specifically, one man, my
boy Andrew Carnegie, saw this and
decided to create a new ideology and
called it his quote gospel of wealth.
This book doesn't reject anything new.
In fact, it openly accepts inequality,
capitalism, and elite dominance as
natural. What it does differently is add
a moral responsibility. The big argument
of this book is that the rich deserve
their wealth, but they must use it
wisely for the public good. And believe
it or not, it for the most part actually
works. This idea will cause
contributions that create libraries,
universities, museums, hospitals, and
lots more urban improvements. So, at
least one person on our big three list
is doing good for the world. Just one,
though. This video is not about the
progressive era. It does kind of
establish the roots to the later
progressive movements, but we aren't
quite there yet. The big idea with this
topic is obviously with these horrible
societal inequities, there are going to
be lots of people beginning to push for
reform. This will typically split into a
lot of groups. We're going to talk about
each of them. To start off, socialists
and radical labor leaders like Eugene V.
Debs argued that capitalism exploited
workers and that major industries should
be publicly owned. This group was linked
to many strikes such as the Pullman one
talked about in a previous video. Then
you have the social gospel movement.
People like Washington Gladen will argue
for a religious response to poverty.
They argued Christianity should address
inequality, labor conditions, and urban
poverty. And finally, you have the
utopians, agrarians, and critics. These
movements were less important
individually and had similar arguments,
which is why I'm lumping them all
together. They pretty much all
criticized monopolies, wage labor, and
urban misery. All right, moving on.
Let's talk about women. We already
talked about Jane Adams and her whole
house, but you have to understand in
this time period, women couldn't vote
and had very limited legal power. So, a
response you'll see to this is the
constant use of voluntary organizations
to exert influence. Yes, you have the
reformers and yes, you have the
organizations, but you see a common
trend of what most women in these
organizations were pushing for.
Temperance, child labor reform, public
health, education, and anti-ynching
activism. Time to talk about some
macroeconomic principles, meaning we're
going to switch over to my lovely
economics background. Man, this
background brings back so many memories
of when I actually tried to review AP
economics on this channel. Got to say,
glad I didn't finish those courses.
Anyway, let's talk about what the term
LZ fair means. When I plug it into
Google Translate, it literally means in
French, let it happen. And this actually
perfectly explains the concept. If you
are adopting a LZ fair mentality, it
means you are taking a hands-off
approach. You don't intervene at all and
let all problems get solved without any
intervention. Moving back over to our
history background, there were
increasing debates over whether the
government should be involved in
regulating businesses and had a hand in
their own economics. And I'm sure you
can guess the result. The US will choose
to adopt a lair mentality. However, you
do see attempts to intervene like the
Interstate Commerce Act and the Sherman
Antirust Act, but those governmental
actions will be poorly enforced. In
fact, a good example to counter these
points is President Grover Cleveland's
veto to sending relief to farmers. This
shows the US actively refusing to help
their own economy in hardship. But
here's your contradiction. Because while
the US government didn't intervene at
home, they definitely intervened around
the world. The point is the US wants
more markets and more resources. Your
two examples to memorize here is the US
attaining the lovely Hawaii and Alaska.
Hawaii was attained for access to the
sugar industry and Alaska was attained
for its positioning and resources. There
are also other examples, but you don't
necessarily need to know them all. To
close out this unit, we're going to talk
about politics. Throughout US history,
we've gone through many political
parties. For the Guilded Age, the US has
settled on the Republicans and
Democrats. Republicans were strongest in
the North, were often backed by big
businesses and industry, and supported
high tariffs along with gold standard
currency. Democrats were strongest in
the South. They often drew support from
farmers and immigrants, and they liked
low tariffs, and they were more likely
to support something like free silver as
the currency system. The ironic part
here is that these parties actually had
a lot similar to one another. They both
were pro business. They both avoided
major reform. They both still relied on
Civil War loyalty for votes. And most of
all, they both were horribly corrupt.
Let's zoom in on the corruption.
Something called political machines
traded jobs and aid for votes,
especially in immigrant neighborhoods.
Now, they were corrupt, but they also
filled a welfare gap the government
ignored. A good example of this was
Tamonn Hall in New York City. The
Pendleton Civil Service Act tried to fix
this by creating merit-based federal
jobs. But even with this, distrust in
government still stayed high. And this
is where some agrarian activists will
form the people's party or rather better
known as the populist movement. Pretty
much this movement will argue that the
government should protect ordinary
people, not corporations. That means
free silver, a graduated income tax, a
regulation on railroads, and a lot more
things will be argued for. A democratic
leader who championed key populist
ideals is a man named William Jennings
Brian. He's best known for his famous
cross of gold speech where he argued
that ordinary Americans shouldn't be
quote crucified upon a cross of gold,
condemning the gold standard and calling
for free silver to expand the money
supply. Now, this speech is a little
complex to understand, but to simplify
it, all he was really trying to do is
expand money policies to try and help
farmers and laborers. So, basically, the
common citizen. Now, even though
populists won't be elected for any
presidential elections, you will see
their ideas come up again in
progressivism and the New Deal. And why
don't we call it a day there? And guess
what everybody? Unit 6 is officially
over. Please do consider watching this
video and subscribing to this channel as
it is my non-educational channel. If you
are someone who took the AP exam in
2025, I do apologize for being so late
with this video, but that's in the past
now. Thanks for whoever is still here
watching this video, and I will see you
in unit 7.